Day after day, the spider waited head down for an idea to come to her. Hour by
hour, she sat motionless, deep in thought.
Having promised Wilbur that she would save his life, she was determined to keep her promise,
Charlotte was naturally patient.
She knew from experience that if she waited long enough, a fly would come to
her web, and she felt sure that if she thought long enough about Wilbur's
problem, an idea would come to her mind.
Finally, one morning toward the middle of July, the idea came. Why, how
perfectly simple, she said to herself.
The way to save Wilbur's life is to play a trick on Zuckerman. If I can fool a
bug, thought Charlotte, I can surely fool a man. People are not as smart as bugs.
Wilbur walked into his yard just at that moment. "What are you thinking about,
Charlotte?" he asked. "I was just thinking," said the spider. "That people
are very gullible." "What does gullible mean?" "Easy to fool," said Charlotte.
"That's a mercy," replied Wilbur, and he lay down in the shade of his fence and
went fast asleep.
The spider, however, stayed wide awake, gazing affectionately at him and making
plans for his future. Summer was half gone. She knew she didn't have much
time. That morning, just as Wilbur fell asleep, Avery Arable wandered into the
Zuckerman's front yard, followed by Fern. Avery carried a live frog in his hand.
Fern had a crown of daisies in her hair.
The children ran for the kitchen. "Just in time for a piece of blueberry pie,"
said Mrs. Zuckerman. "Look at my frog," said Avery, placing the frog on the
drain board and holding out his hand for pie. "Take that thing out of here," said
Mrs. Zuckerman. "He's hot," said Fern.
"He's almost dead, that frog." "He is not," said Avery. He lets me scratch him
between the eyes. The frog jumped and landed in Mrs. Zuckermanman's dishpan full of soapy water.
You're getting your pow on you, said Fern. Can I look for eggs in the hen
house and Edith? Run outdoors, both of you, and don't bother the hens.
It's getting all over everything, shouted Fern. His pie is all over his
front. Come on, frog! cried Avery. He scooped up his frog. The frog kicked,
splashing soapy water onto the blueberry pie. "Another crisis!" groaned Fern.
"Let's swing in the swing," said Avery.
The children ran to the barn.
Mr. Zuckerman had the best swing in the county. "It was a single long piece of
heavy rope tied to the beam over the north doorway. At the bottom end of the
rope was a fat knot to sit on. It was arranged so that you could swing without
being pushed. You climbed a ladder to the hoft. Then, holding the rope, you
stood at the edge and looked down and were scared and dizzy. Then you
straddled the knot so that it acted as a seat. Then you got up all your nerve,
took a deep breath, and jumped.
For a second you seemed to be falling to the barn floor far below. But then
suddenly the rope would begin to catch you and you would sail through the barn
door going a mile a minute with the wind whistling in your eyes and ears and
hair. Then you would zoom upward into the sky and look up at the clouds and
the rope would twist and you would twist and turn with the rope.
Then you would drop down down down out of the sky and come sailing back into
the barn, almost into the hoft. Then sail out again, not quite so far this
time. Then in again, not quite so high.
Then out again. Then in again, then out.
Then in. And then you jump off and fall down and let somebody else try it.
Mothers for miles around worried about Zuckermanman's swing. They feared some
child would fall off, but no child ever did. Children almost always hang on to
things tighter than their parents think they will. Avery put the frog in his
pocket and climbed to the hoft. "The last time I swang in this swing, I
almost crashed into a barn swallow," he yelled. "Take that frog out!" ordered Fern.
Avery straddled the rope and jumped. He sailed out through the door, frog and
all, and into the sky. Frog and all.
Then he sailed back into the barn. Your tongue is purple, screamed Fern. So is
yours, cried Avery, sailing out again with the frog. I have hay inside my
dress. It itches, called Fern. Scratch it, yelled Avery as he sailed back. It's
my turn, said Fern. Jump off. Fern's got the itch, sang Avery.
When he jumped off, he threw the swing up to his sister. She shut her eyes
tight and jumped. She felt the dizzy drop, then the supporting lift of the
swing. When she opened her eyes, she was looking up into the blue sky and was
about to fly back through the door. They took turns for an hour.
When the children grew tired of swinging, they went down toward the
pasture and picked wild raspberries and ate them. Their tongues turned from
purple to red. Fern bit into a raspberry that had a bad tasting bug inside it and
got discouraged. Avery found an empty candy box and put his frog in it. The
frog seemed tired after his morning in the swing. The children walked slowly up
toward the barn. They too were tired and hardly had energy enough to walk.
"Let's build a treehouse," suggested Avery. "I want to live in a tree with my
frog." "I'm going to visit Wilbur," Fern announced. They climbed the fence into
the lane and walked lazily toward the pig pen. Wilbur heard them coming and
got up. Avery noticed the spiderweb and coming closer he saw Charlotte. "Hey,
look at that big spider," he said. "It's tremendous." "Leave it alone," commanded
Fern. "You've got a frog. Isn't that enough?"
That's a fine spider, and I'm going to capture it," said Avery. He took the
cover off the candy box. Then he picked up a stick. "I'm going to knock that old
spider into this box," he said. Wilbur's heart almost stopped when he saw what
was going on. "This might be the end of Charlotte if the boy succeeded in
catching her." "You stop it, Avery!"
cried Fern.
Avery put one leg over the fence of the pig pin. He was just about to raise his
stick to hit Charlotte when he lost his balance. He swayed and toppled and
landed on the edge of Wilbur's trough.
The trough tipped up and then came down with a slap. The goose egg was right
underneath. There was a dull explosion as the egg broke and then a horrible smell.
Fern screamed. Avery jumped to his feet.
The air was filled with the terrible gases and smells from the rotten egg.
Templeton, who had been resting in his home, scuttled away into the barn. "Good
night!" screamed Avery. "Good night!
What a stink! Let's get out of here!"
Fern was crying. She held her nose and ran toward the house. Avery ran after
her, holding his nose. Charlotte felt greatly relieved to see him go. It had
been a narrow escape.
Later on that morning, the animals came up from the pasture, the sheep, the
lambs, the gander, the goose, and the seven gosslings. There were many
complaints about the awful smell, and Wilbur had to tell the story over and
over again of how the arable boy had tried to capture Charlotte, and how the
smell of the broken egg drove him away just in time. "It was that rotten goose
egg that saved Charlotte's life," said Wilbur.
The goose was proud of her share in the adventure. Oh, I'm delighted that the
egg never hatched," she gabbled.
Templeton, of course, was miserable over the loss of his beloved egg, but he
couldn't resist boasting. "It pays to save things," he said in his surirly
voice. "A rat never knows when something is going to come in handy. I never throw
anything away."
Well, said one of the lambs, this whole business is all well and good for
Charlotte, but what about the rest of us? The smell is unbearable.
Who wants to live in a barn that is perfumed with rotten egg? "Don't worry,
you'll get used to it," said Templeton.
He sat up and pulled wisely at his long whiskers, then crept away to pay a visit
to the dump.
When Lurvy showed up at lunchtime carrying a pale of food for Wilbur, he
stopped short a few paces from the pig pin. He sniffed the air and made a face.
"What in thunder?" he said, setting the pale down. He picked up the stick that
Avery had dropped and pried the trough up. "Rats," he said. "Ph, I might have known a rat
would make a nest under this trough. How I hate a rat."
And Lurvy dragged Wilbur's trough across the yard and kicked some dirt into the
rat's nest, burying the broken egg and all Templeton's other possessions.
Then he picked up the pale. Wilbur stood in the trough, drooling with hunger.
Lurvy poured. The slops ran creamily down around the pig's eyes and ears.
Wilbur grunted. He gulped and sucked and sucked and gulped, making swishing and
swishing noises, anxious to get everything at once.
It was a delicious meal. Skim milk, wheat midlings, leftover pancakes, half
a donut, the rind of a summer squash, two pieces of stale toast, a third of a
ginger snap, a fishtail, one orange peel, several noodles from a noodle
soup, the scum off a cup of cocoa, an ancient jelly roll, a strip of paper
from the lining of the garbage pail, and a spoonful of raspberry Jell-O.
Wilbur ate heartily. He planned to leave half a noodle and a few drops of milk
for Templeton. Then he remembered that the rat had been useful in saving
Charlotte's life and that Charlotte was trying to save his life. So he left a
whole noodle instead of a half.
Now that the broken egg was buried, the air cleared and the barn smelled good
again. The afternoon passed and evening came. Shadows lengthened. The cool and
kindly breath of evening entered through the doors and windows.
A stride her web, Charlotte sat moodily, eating a horsefly and thinking about the
future. After a while she burred herself.
She descended to the center of the web, and there she began to cut some of her
lines. She worked slowly but steadily while the other creatures drowsed. None
of the others, not even the goose, noticed that she was at work. Deep in
his soft bed, Wilbur snoozed. Over in their favorite corner, the golings whistled a night song.
Charlotte tore quite a section out of her web, leaving an open space in the
middle. Then she started weaving something to take the place of the
threads she had removed. When Templeton got back from the dump around midnight,
the spider was still at work.
Chapter 11.
The miracle.